Guide to the Northern Pacific Railway Company Records 1870-1968
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Northern Pacific Railway Company Records
1870-1968
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 128
Northern Pacific Railway Company
228.5 linear feet, 24 moving image items, 32 oversize volumes, and 3 oversize boxes. 412 boxes, 20 film reels, 4 VHS tapes, 32 oversize volumes, and 3 oversize boxes. Materials in this collection are generally in good structural condition but are quite dusty. Most materials were housed in poor conditins prior to donation to the Archives. Such materials accumulated extensive amounts of dust and pollens; some sustained minor water damage; and several bound volumes are shedding leather debris.
The Northern Pacific Railway Company was a transcontinental railroad that crossed Minnesota, Wisconsin, North Dakota, Montana, Idaho, Washington, and Oregon. This collection includes both bound and unbound correspondence, construction and expense reports, financial ledgers, right-of-way descriptions and maps, activity logs, publicity materials (including photographs and film reels), and personnel records created by employees of the Northern Pacific Railway Company and its subsidiary lines between the years 1870 and 1968--though materials are predominantly from the late 1880s through the early 1940s.
Historical Note
The first survey for a northern route to the Pacific was conducted by the War Department in 1853. The Northern Pacific Railroad Company was organized in 1864 with Josiah Perman as president. Construction began at Carlton, Minnesota, in February 1870, with an initial operation of 125 miles. That same year, construction began at Kalama, Washington Territory, near Portland, Oregon, and that line was extended to New Tacoma, Washington Territory, by 1873. The company was reorganized in the wake of financial troubles in 1875. The western and eastern lines joined at Gold Creek, Montana, in 1883. The real completion date was 1888 when the tunnel through Stampede Pass, Washington, was opened, replacing a switchback line over that pass. The company was reorganized for a second time in 1896 as the Northern Pacific Railway Company.
The company’s lines were organized into divisions. According to the 1881 annual report, the divisions were as follows:
Wisconsin Division: Brainerd, Minnesota to Dulluth, Minnesota
Minnesota Division: Minnesota/North Dakota border to Great Lakes
Dakota Division: Bismarck, North Dakota to North Dakota/Minnesota border
Missouri Division: Bismarck, North Dakota to Miles City, Montana
Yellowstone Division: Miles City, Montana to Livingston, Montana
Rocky Mountain Division: Livingston, Montana to Missoula, Montana
Clark’s Fork Division: Missoula, Montana to Montana/Idaho border
Pend D’Oreille Division: Montana/Idaho border to Ainsworth, Washington
Cascade Division: Ainsworth, Washington to Tacoma, Washington
Pacific Division: Tacoma, Washington to Portland, Oregon
The geographic boundaries of divisions changed over time. They were originally based on the distance an engine could go before it needed service and fuel, a distance that became greater with changes in engine technology.
Under its charter, the Northern Pacific could not build branch lines to feed into the main line. In order to meet its needs for feeder lines and other cooperative transportation ventures, the main company formed separate corporations to construct connecting lines. These small rail and other transportation lines were then sold to the parent company, which under its charter was able to acquire previously constructed lines.
The Astoria and Columbia River Railroad Company was incorporated on April 4, 1895. It operated between Seaside and Goble, Oregon, from May 1898 to March 1911. Its predecessor was the Seashore Railroad Company. By 1909 it was an operating subsidiary of the Spokane, Portland and Seattle Railway Company until the two companies merged in 1911.
The Camp Creek Railway Company was incorporated June 8, 1911, and built from Manhattan to Anceny, Montana. It opened its line in 1912, and sold to the NPRR in June 1914.
The Central Washington Railroad Company operated a line from Cheney to Coulee City, Washington.
The Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad Company was incorporated on February 14, 1855. It operated main lines from Chicago, IL, to St. Paul, Minnesota, and to St. Louis, MO, and Cody, Wyoming. Like the Northern Pacific, it created and absorbed numerous branch and predecessor lines. Also like the NPRR, it became a part of the Burlington Northern Railroad Company in 1970.
The Clearwater Short Line Railway Company was incorporated on November 9, 1898, and sold to the Northern Pacific Railway Company on June 23, 1914. Its main lines were from Riparia, Washington, to Grangeville, Stites, and Headquarters, Idaho.
The Coeur d’Alene Railway and Navigation Company was incorporated on July 6, 1886, and was leased to the NPRR in 1888. Its main line ran from Cataldo, Idaho to the Montana state line near Mullan, Idaho. It was sold in foreclosure to the NPRR on January 26, 1897.
The Connell Northern Railway Company was incorporated on June 1, 1909. It operated between Connell and Adco, Washington, between in 1910 and 1914. It was sold to the NPRR on June 25, 1914.
The Drummond and Phillipsburg Railroad Company was incorporated on January 17, 1887 and sold to the Northern Pacific and Montana Railroad Company on September 7, 1888. It operated a line between Drummond and Phillipsburg, Montana. There was also an extension to Rumsey, Montana, that was abandoned in 1904.
The Dixon-Polson Line operated between Dixon and Polson, Montana.
The Gaylord and Ruby Valley Railway Company was incorporated on March 29, 1897 and sold to the NPRR on February 28, 1899. It started a line from Renovo, Montana, to Twin Bridges, Montana; construction was completed by the NPRR.
The Great Northern Railway Company was originally the St. Paul, Minneapolis and Manitoba Railroad Company (incorporated May 23, 1879); the St. Paul and Pacific Railroad Company (incorporated March 10, 1862), and the Minneapolis and St. Cloud Railroad Company (incorporated March 1, 1956). The first division of the St. Paul and Pacific Railroad Co. completed its first line from St. Paul to Minneapolis in 1862. The Great Northern Railway Company was formed on September 18, 1889 and involved the purchase or absorption of these and numerous other lines. Originally operating in Minnesota and the Midwest, the company completed its line from Duluth and St. Paul, Minnesota, to Everett and Seattle, Washington in 1893. It was the only line to build to the west coast without federal land grants.
The Green River and Northern Railroad Company was incorporated on September 22, 1890 and was sold to the NPRR on April 21, 1898. It was a branch line that joined the NPRR system at Palmer Junction in western Washington state.
The Kootenai Valley Railroad Company was incorporated on October 19, 1898. Its main line ran from Bonners Ferry, Idaho, to Porthill, Idaho, on the Canadian border. It was sold to and merged into the Great Northern Railway Company in 1913.
The Livingston-Gardner Branch operated from Livingston to Gardner, Montana.
The Missoula and Bitter Root Valley Railroad Company was incorporated on January 4, 1887. It operated a line from Missoula, Montana, to Grantsdale, Montana, 1888. That same year, it was incorporated into the Northern Pacific and Montana Railroad Company.
The Missouri River Railway Company was incorporated June 13, 1906, in North Dakota. It built track from Glendive to Sidney, Montana, and from Cannon Ball to Stanton, North Dakota. It was sold to the NPRR on June 20, 1914.
The Northern Pacific and Montana Railway Company was formed of the Drummond and Phillipsburg Railroad Company, the Helena and Northern Railroad Company, the Helena, Boulder Valley and Butte Railroad Company, and the Missoula and Bitter Root Valley Railroad Company in 1888. Its main lines ran from Logan, Montana to Butte and from De Smet, Montana, to the Idaho state line. There were also numerous branch lines.
The Northern Pacific and Puget Sound Shore Railroad Company was incorporated on August 23, 1884. Its main line operated between Meeker and Seattle, Washington, with branch lines to Kennydale and from Kirkland Junction to Kirkland. It was sold to the NPRR on April 21, 1898.
The Peninsular Branch operated between Shelton and Gordonville, Washington.
The Port Townsend and Southern Railroad was incorporated on September 28, 1887 and operated from 1890 to 1914. Its predecessor was the Olympia and Chehalis Valley Railroad Company. Its main lines from between Tenino and Olympia and between Port Townsend and Quilcene, Washington. The main line was sold to the NPRR in 1914; the line was then sold to Joshua Green in 1917.
The Puget Sound Shore Railroad was incorporated on August 19, 1882. It operated a line between Stuck Junction (south of Kent, Washington) to Seattle. It was sold to the Northern Pacific and Puget Sound Shore Railroad Company October 31, 1889, which was in turn sold to the NPRR on April 21, 1898.
The Rocky Fork and Cooke City Railway Company was incorporated on December 10, 1886. It operated a line from Laurel, Montana, to Red Lodge, Montana. It was sold to and merged into the NPRR on April 21, 1898.
The St. Paul and Duluth Railroad Company was incorporated June 28, 1877. It was sold to the NPRR on June 15, 1900.
The St. Paul and Northern Pacific Railway Company was sold to the NPRR on November 2, 1896.
The Seattle and International Railway Company was incorporated on June 30, 1896. Its main line ran from Seattle, Washington, to Sumas, on the Washington-British Columbia border, which it purchased as the Seattle, Lake Shore and Eastern Railway Company. It operated from July 1896 to March 1901, when it was sold to the NPRR.
The Seattle, Lake Shore and Eastern Railway Company was incorporated on April 28, 1885. Its two main lines ran from Seattle, Washington, to Sumas, on the Washington-British Columbia border, and from Spokane Falls to Davenport, Washington. It was sold in foreclosure in July 1896—the eastern portion to the Spokane and Seattle Railway Company, the western portion to the Seattle and International Railway Company. These were, in turn sold to the NPRR, in 1900 and 1901.
The Shields River Valley Railway Company was incorporated October 24, 1908 and built a line from Mission to Wilsall, Montana. It was sold to and merged into the NPRR on June 23, 1914.
The Spokane Falls and Idaho Railroad was formed on October 25, 1886. Its main line was from Hauser Junction, near the Washington-Idaho border, to Coeur d’Alene. It operated from 1886 to 1898, when it was sold to the NPRR.
The Spokane and Palouse Railway Company was incorporated in 1886. It operated a line from Marshall, Washington, to Genesee and Juliaetta, Idaho from 1886 to 1899. It was sold to the NPRR on February 21, 1899.
The Tacoma, Olympia and Grays Harbor Railroad Company was formed on May 7, 1890. Its main line ran between Lakeview and Ocosta, Washington, on Grays Harbor. It was sold to the United Railroads of Washington on August 2, 1890, which was in turn sold to the NPRR on April 21, 1898.
The Washington and Columbia River Railway Company was incorporated on August 4, 1892. Its main line ran from Pendleton, Oregon, to Dayton, Washington, through Wallula and Walla Walla, Washington. It operated from 1892 to 1907, when it was sold to the NPRR.
The Western Dakota Railway Company was formed on June 13, 1906. It was sold to the NPRR on June 20, 1914.
The Yakima and Pacific Coast Railroad Company was formed on May 1, 1890. It operated a line from Chehalis to South Bend, Washington. On February 13, 1892, it was sold to the United Railroads of Washington. This was sold to the NPRR on April 21, 1898.
The Northern Pacific carried passengers and freight throughout the western United States and was crucial part of the settlement and commerce of the area. In 1970, the Northern Pacific, the Chicago, Burlington and Quincy, and the Great Northern merged to form Burlington Northern Railroad Company.
This collection includes both bound and unbound correspondence, construction and expense reports, financial ledgers, right-of-way descriptions and maps, activity logs, publicity materials (including photographs and film reels), and personnel records created by employees of the Northern Pacific Railway Company and its subsidiary lines between the years 1870 and 1968--though materials are predominantly from the late 1880s through the early 1940s.
The Northern Pacific Railway Records present an extensive and detailed resource for researching railroad corporate management structures, land ownership histories for railroad associated properties (particularly in North Dakota, Montana, Idaho, and Washington state), economic impacts created by railroad construction and repair, corporate investment into raw material production for cheap construction supplies (particularly timber), and NPRR marketing strategies spanning a period of dramatic social and economic change in the American West. Correspondence records in this collection provide significant insights into prevailing railroad management structures during the late 19th and early 20th Centuries--when the rail industry dominated the social, economic, and political realms of rural American life. As was common during the time period, NPRR field operation managers were required to be technical experts as well as administrators. The records generated and/or compiled by the railroad's engineering staff reveal this complex balance of designing construction projects, scheduling traffic flows, and managing day-to-day operations. Rights-of-way documents, property maps, and construction drawings form a uniquely valuable resource for researching individual real estate histories and large-scale settlement patterns. The financial records in this collection provide detailed accounts of occupations and pay schedules for railroad personnel, the corporation's purchases of construction materials and sundry supplies (often specific to individual stations), and freight volumes carried from the region to national markets. The NPRR promotional department records in this collection preserve sometimes overt and often subtle techniques intended to both create and reinforce the railroad's preferred images of life in the Rocky Mountain West and Pacific Northwest. These promotional materials form a particularly interesting body of evidence for comparison and contrast with perceptions presented by contemporary regional literatures as well as the department's focus on highlighting agricultural abundance during periods of drought and farm foreclosures.
Materials in this collection were predominantly generated or compiled by engineering and promotions personnel. For the most part, engineering department recording procedures are consistent; however, the materials in sub-group 2 were generated by subsidiary and associated rail lines that reflect widely varrying recording policies and project goals. Additionally, NPRR engineers tended to move frequently, causing some degree of discontinuity.
The collection is divided into three subgroups: Engineering Department; Branch Lines, Predecessors and Related Companies; and Advertising and Publicity Department.
The collection is further divided into sixty-one series:
Subgroup 1: Engineering Department, 165.25 linear feet and 14 oversize volumes, 1870 - 1968
Series I: Main line General, 22 linear feet and 3 oversize volumes, 1870 - 1965
Series II: Second Main Line, 33 linear feet, 1905 - 1956
Series III: Main line office, Helena, 0.25 linear feet and 5 oversize volumes, 1887 - 1893
Series IV: Idaho Division (Montana/Idaho), 1.0 linear feet, 1881 - 1900
Series V: Clarks Fork and Pend d’Oreille Division (Montana/Idaho), 3.5 linear feet, 1881 - 1910
Series VI: Missoula Division (Montana/Idaho), 6.0 linear feet, 1906 - 1909
Series VII: Missouri Division (Montana/Idaho), 4.0 linear feet, 1891 - 1912
Series VIII: Montana Division (Montana/Idaho), 1 volume, 1913
Series IX: Rocky Mountain Division (Montana/Idaho), 25.0 linear feet, 1882 - 1961
Series X: Yellowstone Division (Montana/Idaho), 0.75 linear feet, 1881 - 1953
Series XI: General Oregon/Washington, 28.0 linear feet, 1880 - 1910
Series XII: Cascade Division (Oregon/Washington), 7.5 linear feet and 3 oversize volumes, 1882 - 1892
Series XIII: Pacific Division (Oregon/Washington), 4.5 linear feet and 1 oversize volume, 1871 - 1909
Series XIV: Portland Division (Oregon/Washington), 1.25 linear feet, 1881 - 1909
Series XV: Seattle Division (Oregon/Washington), 0.25 linear feet, 1901 - 1905
Series XVI: Western Division (Oregon/Washington), 4.0 linear feet and 1 oversize volume, 1883 - 1907
Series XVII: Yakima Division (Oregon/Washington), 1.5 linear feet, 1883 - 1889
Series XVIII: Dakota Division, 2.25 linear feet, 1883 - 1910
Series XIX: Minnesota Division, 7.5 linear feet, 1881 - 1960
Series XX: Wisconsin Division, 2.5 linear feet, 1881 - 1893
Series XXI: Other Construction Projects and Unidentified, 8.5 linear feet and 1 oversize volume, 1881 - 1968
Series XXII: Photographs, 2.0 linear feet, 1882 - 1959
Subgroup 2: Branch Lines, Predecessors and Related Companies, 60.75 linear feet and 18 oversize volumes, 1881 - 1960
Series XXIII: Astoria and Columbia River Railroad Company, 1 folder, 1894 - 1898
Series XXIV: Bear Creek Western Railway Company, 1 folder, 1901 - 1910
Series XXV: Camp Creek Railway Company, 1.0 linear feet and 1 oversize volume, 1911 - 1912
Series XXVI: Central Washington Railroad Company, 4.5 linear feet and 3 oversize volumes, 1888 - 1910
Series XXVII: Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad Company, 5.5 linear feet, 1900 - 1960
Series XXVIII: Clearwater Short Line Railway Company, 15.5 linear feet, 1890 - 1910
Series XXIX: Coeur d’Alene Railway and Navigation Company, 2.0 linear feet, 1883 - 1892
Series XXX: Connell Northern Railway Company, 0.25 linear feet, 1909 - 1910
Series XXXI: Dixon-Polson Line, 0.5 linear feet, 1913 - 1958
Series XXXII: Drummond and Phillipsburg Railroad Company, 0.25 linear feet, 1887 - 1888
Series XXXIII: Gaylord and Ruby Valley Railway Company, 1.0 linear feet, 1897 - 1902
Series XXXIV: Grays Harbor and Columbia River Railway Company, 0.25 linear feet, 1901 - 1909
Series XXXV: Great Northern Railway Company, 1 oversize volume, 1909
Series XXXVI: Green River and Northern Railroad Company, 0.5 linear feet and 1 oversize volume, 1887 - 1891
Series XXXVII: Kootenai Valley Railroad Company, 1 bound volume, 1890
Series XXXVIII: Livingston-Gardner Branch, 0.25 linear feet, 1922 - 1960
Series XXXIX: Manitoba Southwestern Colonization Railway, 1 folder, 1881 - 1882
Series XL: Missoula and Bitter Root Valley Railroad Company, 1 partial reel of microfilm and 2 bound volumes, 1887 - 1888
Series XLI: Missouri River Railway Company, 8.25 linear feet, 1909 - 1912
Series XLII: Northern Pacific and Montana Railway Company, 2.0 linear feet, 1883 - 1908
Series XLIII: Northern Pacific and Puget Sound Shore Railroad Company, 1.25 linear feet, 1882 - 1891
Series XLIV: Peninsular Branch (Washington), 1.25 linear feet, 1901 - 1906
Series XLV: Port Townsend and Southern Railroad, 1 bound volume, 1906 - 1907
Series XLVI: Puget Sound Shore Railroad, 1 bound volume, 1891
Series XLVII: Rocky Fork and Cooke City Railway Company, 0.5 linear feet, 1889 - 1890
Series XLVIII: St. Paul and Duluth Railroad Company, 0.5 linear feet, 1892 - 1898
Series XLIX: St. Paul and Northern Pacific Railway Company, 0.25 linear feet, 1885 - 1887
Series L: Seattle and International Railway Company, 2 bound volumes (one is oversize), 1900 - 1904
Series LI: Seattle, Lake Shore and Eastern Railway Company, 1 bound volume, 1893
Series LII: Shields River Valley Railway Company, 2.0 linear feet, 1908 - 1910
Series LIII: Spokane Falls and Idaho Railroad, 0.25 linear feet, 1888 - 1891
Series LIV: Spokane and Palouse Railway Company, 4.0 linear feet and 4 oversize volumes, 1885 - 1907
Series LV: Tacoma, Olympia and Grays Harbor Railroad Company, 3.5 linear feet and 3 oversize volumes, 1890 - 1892
Series LVI: Tacoma Terminal Company, 2.5 linear feet, 1887 - 1893
Series LVII: Washington and Columbia River Railway Company, 0.25 linear feet, 1898 - 1902
Series LVIII: Western Dakota Railway Company, 0.5 linear feet, 1909 - 1913
Series LIX: Yakima and Pacific Coast Railroad Company, 1.0 linear feet and 3 oversize volumes, 1890 - 1893
Subgroup 3: Advertising and Publicity Department, 2.5 linear feet, 24 moving image items, and 2 oversize boxes, 1895 - 1950
Series LX: Moving Images, 20 16mm film reels and 4 VHS tapes, circa 1920s - 1940
Series LXI: Publicty Photographs, 2.5 linear feet and 2 oversize boxes, 1895 - 1950
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
The custodial history of these records is largely unknown. One group of records received in 1970 had been stored in the Northern Pacific depot in Missoula, Montana, until their transfer to the archives after the creation of Burlington Northern Railroad. Some of the materials may have been discarded from the Minnesota Historical Society’s NPRR collection, or may have been received directly from the NPRR.
Gift, in part, of Burlington Northern Railroad, 1970.
All previously separated materials were either re-integrated into the collection as described in the processing notes or were deaccessioned.
The majority of the Northern Pacific Records are held by the Minnesota Historical Society in St. Paul, Minnesota. Their collection includes approximately 10,600 cubic feet of records that date from 1861 to 1970.
There are also numerous records held by the Minnesota Transportation Museum in St. Paul, Minnesota.
Minnesota State University in Mankato holds a collection of NPRR pamphlets.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.